[Music]
hello good evening good day everybody
welcome to the ask community show
episode
119 welcome and i hope you're all doing
very well
so today we discuss as you know uh
geopolitics history current office and
so on i've as usual taken a lot of
questions
and i'm going to be answering them and
at the end if there is time i will take
some questions from the live chat once
the main bunch of questions is dealt
with
before we get into it let us see who all
is there with us on the live chat i can
see shambhavi
good evening good day all of you
great to be back with you all and with
that let us get into the questions
what are the questions for today let us
take a look
okay question number one is the most
popular question right now everyone
wants to talk about this
uh skandan says what's your take on
crowley xci accepting that cia killed
uh former indian prime minister alvaro
shastri and dr homie jebaba
jesus says namaste what are your views
on a cia agent robert crowley confessing
that the u.s government
got uh mr shastri and dr baba killed
lagera online says your take on the cia
killing
india's nuclear physicist homibaba and
prime minister lal bader shastri
confessions of robert crowley
uh second in command of the cia's
directorate of special of operations
covert operations as recorded in a book
by gregory douglas okay
so this this this is just three
questions lots of people have asked me
about this
so uh yeah okay so let's
let's examine this issue
so uh
this cia agent has apparently confessed
that the u.s got somebody got our prime
minister and dr baba killed
and so on so what is the what is the
story behind this where does this claim
come from where does this claim come
from so this is not exactly a very new
claim let me
share my screen
so this is where this story comes from
it's a book by gregory douglas called
confessions
with
the crow
yeah so this is the book
and who is gregory douglas not quite
sure
and it's about this cia
agent robert trumbull crowley
uh once a leader of the cia's
clandestine operations division
so this uh
person was contacted by the author in
and
several in interviews were done
and this book is a result of those
interviews this book was published in
so it's been around for almost a decade
and if you go into this book
and you read some of these
interviews then you will find that this
individual whoever he is robert trumbull
crowley
apparently makes the claim the claim or
the boast
that the cia got prime minister lal badu
shastra killed and also dr homi baba
killed so that is a claim a boast that
is made during
an interview with this individual crow
called gregory douglas all right
this is by no means any kind of proof
it is
a retired cia guy
making a certain claim making a boast
can we
can we consider this to be proof no
what is the actual evidence
beyond the claim made by some person
there is no other evidence beyond
someone's claim
so uh
my point of view is that it is certainly
possible
somebody else has had asked that is it
so easy
for the americans to get an indian prime
minister killed or an indian nuclear
scientist killed uh
you know in the 1960s and 70s etc it was
much easier than it is today
for it it was much easier for the
americans to get somebody killed
uh even a head of state
even today it may be
it may be possible for them to do that
even today so yeah it is certainly
possible that they could have done such
things
uh it is known that whether it's a cia
whether it's the israeli mossad or
whatever uh they do
undertake such operations
one hears about various uh nuclear
scientists in for example iran getting
assassinated getting killed
and the blame is usually laid on the
doorstep of the doorstep of the mossad
the israeli
secret service intelligence agency right
so these things have happened in the
past yes
uh so it's certainly possible
that the cia may have been behind this
the americans may have been behind
up
what happened now what happened to dr uh
homie baba he died in a mysterious plane
crash
in europe
it was over the swiss or the french alps
i believe the plane crashed there and
and
for decades there was no attempt made to
go and look at the wreckage
and uh
see if there is any survivors or
anything like that
obviously survivors won't last beyond a
few hours if anybody survives
on a high mountain range so for decades
there was no
attempt made to
figure out what happened and to examine
the wreckage so that is very mysterious
for sure it's mysterious
so dr baba died in that plane crash very
mysterious plane crash and uh
prime minister shastri died in tashkent
in the ussr the then ussr right
so it is i would say it is uh
a little far-fetched to believe that the
americans
who were already engaged in this massive
cold war with the soviet union
would have been able to assassinate an
indian prime minister on russian or on
ussr soil it's a little far-fetched to
imagine that unless the ussr itself was
complicit in this sort of in this sort
of operation which again is even more
far-fetched
to imagine to believe
right
so i would say that it's not entirely
impossible
especially in the case of dr homi baba
it is very suspicious the way the plane
crash happened and the way he died and
in the way there was no investigation
conducted either from india
or from or or from france or switzerland
or from from any other country right
that is extremely suspicious so yes
there is something strange that happened
uh uh
in the case of the
death of dr baba in the case of the of
prime minister shasta once again it's
lots of unanswered questions
are there
questions that have still not been
answered uh why was no postmortem
conducted or was it no why was it not
conducted properly even today the cap
that the prime minister was wearing
which was stained with blood and other
fluids is still available even today it
could be examined and one could try to
figure out what exactly
uh
the blood or the body body fluids
contain
the traces of which are still on the cap
in the position of the shastri family so
there's a lot that has not been answered
even in the case of the
depth
the premature death of the indian prime
minister mr shastri
so certainly questions exist certainly
unanswered questions are there
but i would say that this
news that has suddenly reappeared even
though the book was published in 2013
that news uh
is a little bit uh
it's just a claim it's not even a claim
it's a boost
made by a retired cia person a boost
that has me that was made without
providing a single piece of evidence
so that's all we can say i mean if you
start uh
taking
boasts seriously you're you're going
into the territory of conspiracy
theories a conspiracy theory is a claim
that is made without presenting any
evidence whatsoever
right
so as far as we are concerned as of
today we have zero evidence to
substantiate the claim that this
ex-cia agent robert crowley made
there is no evidence to back up to
substantiate the claim and that's why uh
it is hard to take it seriously it is
certainly possible but there is no
evidence for it so that is as far as i
would go with this
if evidence emerges
well then one would have to take it
seriously and it is certainly possible
but
as far as we know there is no evidence
so that's where we are
okay next question ananya says
um thank you
what is your take on the latest uh
status on the russia ukraine war what do
you
do you think russia will achieve its
goals
ah the russia ukraine war is continuing
it is continuing uh
slowly steadily
uh
we don't quite know what exactly is
happening the the mainstream media which
is entirely controlled by the west which
means it's it's entirely controlled by
the us is port is trying to portray uh
russia the the situation as bad for
russia russia is not doing well and so
on but if you look at the ground
realities the russian
advance
is certainly visible on the map russia
controls over a quarter of the
territory of the former ukraine right so
the
map has been essentially permanently
altered
and i believe that the russians whatever
goals they have they uh will achieve
them that's what it looks like unless
the us or nato actually gets involved on
ukrainian territory which would be a
severe escalation that could lead to any
kind of consequences right so i don't uh
see that sort of thing happening i don't
see the americans getting involved
directly i don't see nato getting
involved directly so the russians will
slowly steadily march forward and
whatever objectives they have in mind
they will achieve them i would imagine
that okay let's take a look at the map
obviously because uh
it always helps to take a look at the
map
not this sorry let me remove this
and
let me share the map where is the map
here is the map
so
there's the map so we're talking about
ukraine this part of the world here
so the russians are already in control
of crimea they're in control of the
donbas region which is eastern ukraine
they are in control of the uh part of
ukraine that aborts the azov sea
essentially uh mario paul
and
all that and eventually i suppose they
would want
mikko live and odessa as well they would
essentially i think want to control the
entire black sea coast of ukraine
and maybe even take cave or force some
kind of regime change in kiev
and leave the eastern part of ukraine as
a
leftover rump state that will be
in some ways or essentially a satellite
state of russia so i believe that's what
the overall long-term objective of this
military operation would be that would
be the political objective to uh to
ensure that ukraine is no longer
a threat
uh directly or indirectly for russia's
national interest so that is what the
objective
i think would be
now um
the west has the u.s has imposed massive
amounts of sanctions on russia it's not
worked
it's not worked it's it's actually
backfired right uh one would have
expected that the russian economy would
have been destroyed by the sanctions
the opposite has happened
the russian economy is doing well the
russian ruble
is the best performing it is most likely
the best performing currency in the
whole world right now
you know uh so that's that's the sort of
thing that has happened and they have
been able to achieve this by pegging
their currency to the price of gold so
the russian ruble is essentially a proxy
for gold for actual gold which the us
dollar not is not right the us dollar is
tied to the price of petroleum it's a
petro dollar so um and the thing is the
russian economy is on very strong
footing you know
uh if we look at the gdp
of russia the the overall yearly
national gdp it's not even in the top
ten
and yet the truth is that many of these
gdp figures
are inflated in their fake figures
many of the uh
of the industries and all the
calculations that go into the gdp are
based on
goods
and consumer goods and services that
don't really have any value the real
value
that
is the true value of a nation's gdp is
how much cement you produce how much
steel and iron you produce whatever was
the metrics
in the 1920s and 1930s that is the true
uh basis of of our nation's real gdp how
much agricultural produce do they have
per year and if you look at russia the
fundamentals are very strong it's
essentially an otarkic state which means
they produce everything they're
self-sufficient in natural resources in
minerals in agriculture all these things
so it's almost impossible to destroy
them economically by imposing sanctions
upon them because they don't need
anything actually from the outside world
in
reality they are the major suppliers
of energy to europe whether it is
natural gas or or whatever else
petroleum etc
and
the entirety the whole of europe is
essentially dependent on russian
energy supplies and right now we're
seeing an energy crisis in in europe
created entirely by european actions
yeah
uh they depend on on russia for for gas
natural gas to to
for heating for energy the germans have
pledged to shut down all their nuclear
power plants and and they don't want to
depend on on on coal so where are they
going to get their energy from this this
is a crisis situation the americans are
witnessing this massive
inflation right significant inflation in
the u.s right now they are increasing
their interest rates which is why the
dollar is becoming stronger it's
becoming stronger and stronger since
uh the beginning of the year since since
january 1st 2022 because they're
increasing the interest interest rates
which is why it is uh people want to
invest in the dollar that's why there is
a demand for the dollar and there i
believe they have stopped printing
unnecessary amounts of u.s dollars paper
money which is why the us dollar is is
appreciating in value and yet the u.s
economy is not doing well you're seeing
inflation and all that so russia is
doing well
and the chinese are sitting on the
sidelines and watching carefully they're
taking notes
they're seeing what works what doesn't
work
what the
us response is like
and so on
and they will uh use the lessons they're
learning in the future when the time is
right in their own
agenda
yeah they also have their own agenda and
so on so that is where we are that is
the current situation roughly overall
briefly
and it's the stalemate continues it's
not really a statement the the russians
have the
ukrainians essentially at their mercy
they are in no hurry there is no time
pressure on them they are fighting a
truly old-fashioned war step by step
trench by trench kilometer by kilometer
they're going forward they are
consolidating whatever gains they have
made and uh
they're going on
a couple of months ago people were
saying that the era of tank warfare is
over the tank is obsolete well
that's not quite the case now isn't it
what happened to those stories
and so on so all the disinformation the
propaganda on social media on the
western channels
indian channels as well it's it's it's
falling flat
the russians are doing well
and
so that's where we are that's that's the
situation as of today
okay a couple of questions here lady of
the multiverse says what's your take on
draupadi murmur as the president of
bharat ananya says what are your
thoughts on madam president andropadi
murmu on being the first lady president
of india what is the role of a president
in india do you think this will be
inspirational to indian women and what
national contribution will madam murmur
be able to make to india all right so uh
just a tiny correction which is okay not
not important uh
madame
is not the first lady president she's
the second lady president there was
another lady who was president about a
decade or so ago what was her name i i
can't quite remember her name i can see
her face in my mind's eye but i can't
remember her face not important she did
not well she was not a very
consequential president
uh she came after dr abrahad that lady
so so uh
mrs murmur is going to be the second
lady president of india but the reason
why uh her presidency is is important is
because uh she belongs to a so-called
tribal community right uh so she she
belongs to the santhal
community of uh eastern india jharkhand
i believe right and it's a significant
community and it's classified as tribals
backward apparently backward people or
whatever uh these are classifications
and categorizations that are left over
from the british era and we still
continue to use that
so uh the santhal people are classified
as tribal people now these are
not some random
obscure people
uh in case you don't know in the 19th
century there was a very significant
santhal rebellion
against british against the british
occupation of india this happened in
jharkhand in in west bengal i think it
was in 1855
right a couple of years before the big
war of independence 1857
so the santhals they uh
uh they rebelled against the british
occupation of their territory and
overall of india
in and also against the zamindari system
which was which which predated the
british occupation of india so as we
know
india
suffered a millennium of humiliation a
millennium of foreign occupation roughly
roughly a millennium yeah give or take
give or take so the first part was the
turkic
occupation of india
one one of the components of that was
the bengal
sultanate or whatever you want to call
it right it starts with the destruction
of nalanda by the by the
by bhakti or khilji and then
things go bad things go worse from there
so the turks or the mughals or whatever
you want to call them these invaders
occupiers they imposed what's called the
zamindari system
in which
certain warlords or feudal uh
essentially thugs were given large
pieces of territory from which they
would collect tax and that tax would be
given to the uh
to the mughal emperor or whatever else
whoever the overlord was it was it would
be given to that person to the to their
administration to the government for
what for whatever purpose they saw fit
and this was a deeply exploitative
system it it impoverished and
uh and victimized the citizens of india
right the zamindari system and the
zaminder history continued during the
british era
during the british occupation of india
and eventually the certain zamindari
classes came into existence and that's
what it was so this was deeply
oppressive and typically the people who
lived in forests and people
essentially like people like the sun for
instance were greatly victimized
so the santos rose up in rebellion
against the zamindari system and the
british occupation of india in 1855 uh
the leaders
of this revolt the leaders of this
war for
freedom were four brothers who belonged
whose surname was murmur the same as mrs
dropper the murmur right so their names
were siddhu kanhu and
there were there were four of them
so they led
the the rebellion against the british it
lasted a few months it was eventually
crushed brutally tens of thousands of
the santa santa people were massacred
lots of villages were burned it was very
brutal very cruel and there was a lot of
bloodshed and the rebellion was
eventually crushed so the santhals where
they they
were the first not not actually the
first but they preceded their rebellion
preceded the 1857 war of independence by
two years right
so it's not some obscure
tribe
they are
they have a significant uh role
that they've played in history
so uh there are lots of these so-called
tribal communities in india which are
actually uh financially and economically
economically quite backward now if you
ask any of your history professors they
will say that um
that the tribals of india are the
so-called adivasis or mull nivasas of
india
which is something that
they use the aryan invasion myth to to
make this claim
they said that the adivasis are the
first people to live in india the aryans
came later that sort of nonsense they
spout and they say that the economic
backwardness financial backwardness of
the tribal populations of india is a
consequence of the brutal unjust
oppressive
uh rule of the aryans in india
the question i would like to ask is who
ruled india for the past 1 000 years
was it the so-called aryans or the
hindus who were ruling india for the
past 1000 years
no
it was the foreigners who were occupying
and ruling india for the past 1000 years
every defect
that you see in indian society is a
consequence of that
if
certain communities
and certain sections of indian societies
are deeply oppressed and still
financially very and economically very
backward and they have suffered the
social injustice it is not
whose fault is it it is the fault of the
of of the of the people who ruled
over india who lorded over india over
the past 1000 years
right
so uh
the fact that this lady
mrs dropper murmur has been appointed as
being elected the president of india is
a great step forward
in bringing uh
dignity and and
justice and equality back to all
sections of indian society especially
those that have been
deeply oppressed by the foreign
oppressors and rulers of india over the
past 1000 years so i think it's a very
good step it's a great step forward it
will give a great sense of joy
and pride to those sections of indian
society that have been oppressed deeply
by foreign oppressors and invaders and
occupiers and
it's a great step forward for india it's
a great step forward for women as well
right so overall i think it's it's a
wonderful thing uh
if you look at various academics whether
in india whether abroad they always
try to portray india as a deeply neglect
in egalitarian society they blame it all
on indian culture not on the foreign
occupation of 000 years of the past 1000
years they try to blame the victim every
time they say it is a defect of indian
culture indian culture is
backward
primitive misogynistic blah blah blah
all that all that stuff
so these steps that are being made that
have been made now
they
are a means of combating these lies
these colonial lies that are still being
spread as gospel truth by academics by
journalists by various think tanks and
so on and so forth so i think it's a
very good move and i i congratulate
mrs murmur and i congratulate the prime
minister and the government on taking
this excellent step
and i thank them as well for that
okay sunil singh says
soon after the funeral of shinzo abe
prime minister fumio kishida
promised the people of japan that uh of
that the constitution of japan would be
amended as per shinzo abe shinzo abe's
vision
will they be able to convince america to
leave japan
so uh
so what's happened right now we know
that on
the the shocking assassination
happened of of
former prime minister mr shinzo abe who
was the most most consequential prime
minister japan has ever had especially
since the uh
us occupation of japan began in 1945 and
the the us occupation of japan still
continues okay
so japan is a nation that is under
foreign occupation against u.s under u.s
occupation and japan has had a history
of this revolving door prime
ministership
prime ministers come and go come and go
and they typically are able to do
nothing
and a few prime ministers
made a little bit of a mark like mr
nakasone
and so on but mr abe is the longest
serving prime minister in japan of all
time and the most consequential prime
minister japan has ever had at least in
the past 70 years
and maybe he was the tallest leader that
japan
had as of today and
he was assassinated very recently right
and after his assassination this
election election happened and his
liberal democratic party
was able to acquire was able to win a
two-thirds majority a super majority
in the japanese
parliament right
and currently the leader is mr funo
kishida the prime minister who was
essentially a protege of mr abe so in
this party
mr abe was kind of a king maker even
though he was made even though he
stepped down from the prime ministership
he is citing health reasons he was still
very much active he was still not that
old least i think he still had a decade
of active political life at least left
in him
and he was kind of a king maker so mr
fumio kishida may have been the prime
minister but he was kind of answerable
to mr shinzo abe that's the kind of
situation it was now that uh
that pillar of strength is gone so mr
kishida is on his own the question is
does he have the political strength the
political uh
stature
to carry out a massive change like
amending the constitution of japan the
constitution of japan was created was
written by americans in 1945 it was
imposed upon the people of japan upon
the nation of japan and since 1945 not a
single word has been changed in the
constitution of japan
america essentially controls japan
america is
occupying japan militarily there are
i don't know how many military bases in
japan all across the nation
and various japanese politicians have
alleged that any significant decision
that is made in japanese
in the job in the japanese government in
policy or whatever it is done with the
approval of american generals and the
american government so it's essentially
the us that's running the country now mr
abe
was a nationalist he wanted uh to amend
the constitution and to allow japan to
to have a proper army and to become uh
and and to have an independent
independent foreign policy that's what
mr shinzo abe
sought
now
he
was a man of of considerable stature the
tallest leader in japan he could have
possibly conceivably
been able to possibly
try and do this
right it's not easy it's not easy to do
that even if you have a technical super
majority because
overall the after all is the americans
that run the country they own the
country essentially it's not that easy
it's technically feasible but will will
they have the guts to do it that's the
question mr kishida i'm not sure
if he has the political standing or the
stature to do it and it's quite possible
that in the absence of mr shinzo abe
even the japanese people will not be
convinced
they have been indoctrinated the
japanese people have been indoctrinated
into this this culture of pacifism
they feel a deep sense of shame about
what
japan did rightly or wrongly during
world war ii
uh they are taught that japan must be a
pacifistic country japan must never
fight again japan must not have an army
army bad military bad pacifism good
hints are good that sort of thing has
been drilled into the minds of the
japanese people so right now the people
of japan are concerned with prices and
wages and daily life and medical
services and child care and all those
things and with such fundamental
concerns constitutional revision is kind
of a luxury a luxury item that's how
most japanese i believe would see
the scenario
so in the face of this sort of political
climate
will it be possible for mr kishta to
amend the constitution of japan and
allow japan to have its own
well not a self-defense form force but a
proper army a proper military i think it
would it is uh it's unlikely
that mr kishida may be able to do that i
hope that he is able to do that it could
be good for japan it will be good for
the people of japan for the nation of
japan i think they have suffered enough
in the past 70 years they have paid more
than the price and
i mean
every nation does certain good things
and bad things yeah for sure i'm not
saying that we must condone the certain
actions that the japanese military
did
during the during their world war ii
campaign some of the things they did
were reprehensible and one must condemn
them but there are other nations that
have done far worse
and no one has ever punished them for
that
so i think it would be good for japan
if this constitution is amended that if
they are allowed to have their own
military and their own independent
foreign policy but i think it's a
stretch
to to expect that to happen i think it
will be a very tall order for mr mr
kishida to go ahead and make this happen
i hope it happens but i am
i am not quite sure it will be possible
so
let's see let's hope for the best but
and if it happens it's good for india as
well
if japan is
is able to break free of the shackles of
foreign occupation and have its own
military its own
independent foreign policy it is great
for india india and japan are natural
allies india and japan are
civilizational brothers
japan is a child of indian civilization
so it would be great for india
but will the americans allow that i
think not
all right next
intellectual thinker says
why uh
did andhra ishvakus chutus and nabeera's
rulers
have names such as vasheshti putra
that's an interesting question so what
mr intellectual thinker is talking about
is the various sativa hana rulers
in the deccan region uh the satwahanas
ruled in this region in the deccan
region in southern in southern and
western parts of india central parts of
india as well
in the first and second etc centuries
a.d
right so they were contemporaneous with
the mahaksha trappers in the western
part of india in gujarat in parts of
maharashtra etc the mahaksha tribes were
the indus keithian rulers the great
indus
kitten rulers who controlled gujarat who
controlled the great ports of india with
through which we did trade with rome and
egypt and other uh various empires and
civilizations
so contemporaneous with the mahatrapas
with the indus heathens were the
satohana rulers
and
some of them have names like gotami
putra satakarni
vashishtiputra pulavami and vashishthi
putra satakarni and so on and so forth
so gautami putra satakarani
uh he lived in the first or second
century a.d
it is believed that he was either a
contemporary or
a contemporary of the great uh
indus keithian maha chapter
or maybe he came just a few decades
after nahapana right because several of
the coins of naha panama which are very
abundant several of mahapana's coins
have been found to be struck with
gautama putra shatakarani's uh
symbols
and happens coins are found everywhere
not just in india but also in
in
britain
in rome in the roman regions etc
uh so that demonstrates how far reaching
india's trade was so
this
uh the one of the greatest of the
satwana rulers was gotham
so yes he was called gotami putra why
was he called gotham putra not because
of some brahman gotra but because his
mother's name was gotami balashri
so typically what would happen is that
these uh
kings emperors would have multiple wives
right
polygamy is is something that is
acceptable in in the dharmic culture
so
many of these kings would have two or
three wives
and
each of these wives would bear children
and one of these children would
eventually go on to succeed the father
as the king or the emperor so then this
the new ruler would then identify
himself by the name of his mother to
differentiate him with other from other
children because there will be multiple
children with from multiple wives so
gautame putra's mother was go
satakarani's mother was gautama
so that's why he called himself gautam
now he had two oath reasons one was
pulamavi the other one was also known no
called satakarni so they were both
called vashti putra pulavami and
pashishte putra satakarani
so
the name of the
mother was appended to the given name
of these sons or these kings that's how
it was so it is not named after some
brahmin gothar or whatever gotra they
took the names of their mothers they
appended their mother's names something
putra and then the actual name so gautam
and so on so forth so forth that's how
it was that was the naming system
so uh yeah so they essentially took
their mother's names as their identifier
that's how it was so that's the answer
to your question
okay saurabh says what were the bogas
kale
clay tablets
did they mention vedic gods who was the
methane king
or
did or does all this indicate westward
migration of culture from india and
people from india uh what about some
arguments at first that the first
speakers of sanskrit was the syrians
how can these claims be shattered and so
on okay what are the bogeys kalei clay
tablets so they these um
let me see if i can um
put something up on the screen
bogeys kelly clay tablets i'm not sure i
have that but let me show you something
else
on the screen so we are talking about
the mithanes right so first of all let
me tell you what what basically tablets
were
uh so this was essentially a treaty
between the mithani
kingdom and the hittite kingdom so
to understand where this is you today
take a look at the map because otherwise
you will not get the correct context
where is the map
i had a map somewhere
yeah it's here one second
so we are talking so
let us orient ourselves first you can
see where india is that's where that's
the part of the geography i'm sure you
know so we zoom in a little bit and we
move westwards to the west we have this
temporary nation of pakistan then we
have our persian brothers and sisters
there our persian brethren and sister in
and west of persia we have iraq
and turkey the present-day nation of
turkey which is anatolia and
and to the south of turkey we have syria
so it is in this region that these
kingdoms and empires existed now let me
show you a different
uh
a different map
to put that into better perspective
let's take a look at this
so uh let's zoom in a little
let us wait for that thing to load here
we are so
now that you know which part of the
world you're talking about this is the
two uh kingdoms
the mithani and the hittites
so um
the capital of the methane kingdom was
vashukhani we're not quite sure where it
where it was exactly located we may have
found it we may not have found it but
yeah its capital was vasho khani which
means mine
of great wealth in sanskrit vashukhani
and the capital of the hittite kingdom
was hatusa further to the north west of
the mithani kingdom or empire to the
south you had the egyptian empire the
egyptian pharaohs and to the south
east you had babylonia all right so this
is the geography that we are talking
about now what are we talking about we
are talking about which time period 1500
or so bc
three and a half thousand years before
today okay so about 1500 bc or 1450 bc
somewhere like that there was a treaty
between these two kingdoms between the
methanes and the hittites
so the mithanis were
this kingdom in this region
their aristocracy their ruling class
was indo-aryan they are classified as
indo-iron because they spoke sanskrit
they spoke late
vedic sanskrit
and these
hittites
they also spoke the hittite language
which
seems to have had elements of sanskrit
or maybe their aristocracy also spoke
sanskrit so
yes
so this is present-day syria presented
turkey
that is indeed where the first evidence
of sanskrit is found so they found clay
tablets in this region which uh record
an ancient treaty diplomatic treaty
between the mathani kingdom and the
hittite kingdom uh between the king of
the hittites the king of the muthanis
and it was a peace treaty of sort of
sorts and in this 3d in the text of the
treaty which is in the cuneiform script
the vedic gods
indra varuna and the ashwin twins are
invoked
to witness the treaty and to bless the
treaty
all right so these are vedic gods
indra
who later became zeus who later became
jupiter who later became thor indra
varuna and the ashwin the ashwin twins
these gods were invoked
to witness the treaty as witnesses to
the treaty and to bless the treaty so
that this treaty succeeds
and uh so what's the deal about the the
the mithani their aristocracy their
ruling class spoke sanskrit and they had
like you know
kings
uh with names like tushirata which
essentially means
means he who has a very fast
chariot
tuesday right in sanskrit
so that's the kind of name
this king had
and
the mithani had
extensive diplomatic and family
connections with the pharaohs of egypt
i think the daughter of this king
tusharata
sharatha was married to one of the
pharaohs of egypt i think it was i mean
the first or something like that right
let's take a look at the correspondence
that they had
if i can find it
um
am i able to find okay yeah here we go
here we go let me let me put that on the
screen
so
this king
so he's he uh wrote letters to the
egyptian pharaoh and amenhotep the third
uh around 1370 bc
so they this correspondence is still
available
and i think his daughter married the
egyptian pharaoh and amenhotep the third
and so on
and if you uh
and there's another piece of evidence
from this region from about 1400 1500 bc
the kikuli horse masters a horse
training manual
so this is a hittite manual
in which a hittite horse master named
kikuli
writes an extensive manual on how to
train horses for warfare
now the thing is that this tablet is
written in the hittite language
however there are certain technical
terms technical words that kikuli is not
familiar with in the hittite language
and therefore for certain technical
terms he uses
sanskrit words because apparently he was
better with sanskrit than with the
hittite language
so uh
so very the so the first written
hard evidence of sanskrit is actually
found in this region anatolia and syria
which is why
certain people make the claim that
sanskrit was first poker in syria
yeah
so how do we counter this claim
it's not actually very hard
examine what we have to do is we have to
examine
the sanskrit that is recorded in this
great clay tablets in in these
inscriptions what is the kind of
sanskrit that was that was
written
so on upon examination
and looking at the vocabulary the words
that i use and so on it can be seen that
the sanskrit that the methane and the
hittites used
was late
vedic sanskrit
it was not
proper vedic sanskrit late vedic
sanskrit
it was
later it was it was newer than the
language
that was written that was used for the
rigveda for instance the rig vedic is
the most ancient form of sanskrit that
we know sanskrit has evolved over the
millennia
there is
vedic sanskrit there is late vedic
sanskrit there is then classical
sanskrit which is the line the sanskrit
of the paninion era
and so on and after then you had the
various prakrits the upper branch
languages and so on so the language the
sanskrit the mitani and the hittites
used was late vedic sanskrit it is
it is from a later period than the vedic
age which tells you that these people
would have migrated from india where the
original sanskrit was spoken because
there are certain words that were used
in vedic sanskrit which were not used in
late vedic senses new words arrived in
and this analysis has been done
extensively by uh the scholar mr srikant
talagiri his website is available you
can it's it's all the all the
information is available out there
extensive analysis detailed analysis you
can you can look it up i'm not going to
put it on screen right now because it
will take me time to uh
to pull it out
but yeah if you're interested take a
look at mr srikant talagari's website
and all the information is out there so
the first speakers of sanskrit were not
syrians
the hittites and the mithani
uh they used late vedic sanskrit which
means that they they would have
so if if they were already in as
present in this region as the
aristocracy as the ruling class
about 1500 bc
it means that they would have arrived
there a few centuries before
maybe 2000 bc
yeah and maybe
uh
so so that's the kind of approximate
dating one can arrive at
so it indicates
some sort of westward migration at some
stage in history from india maybe during
the mature so called harappan era of
indian civilization or maybe the late
harappan era of the indian civilization
or something like that
there were lots of waves of migrations
out of india eastwards westwards
around
5000 or so years before today so this
was clearly one of those right
so that's what we can
deduce
from the information that we have at
hand
hardik says who were the native
americans who are the native americans
uh who lives there who i mean who lived
there before the european
settlement there and what happened to
them all right who were the native who
are the native americans once again
let's take a look at the map to
understand uh what part of the world we
are referring to
map
where's the map here it is
so we are talking about the americas and
we talk when we talk about the americas
we mean the north american continent and
the south american continent which is
connected by this
central american region so the original
natives of this of this entire massive
part of the world are called
the native americans
and
so
we know
that in south america
as well as in central america there were
these very highly developed
civilizations the aztecs the mayas the
incas the the toltecs the chimu the
moche and so on and so forth the olmecs
lots
of
highly developed civilizations with
their own writing systems with their own
culture with a very sophisticated
calendar system
uh
you find
if you if you
look in this region in the amazon
rainforest you find extensive
uh settlements in this region entire
cities large cities well-planned cities
with with monumental architecture you
find pyramids and so on so forth so
these are the natives of south america
similarly in central america also you
find similar things in mexico uh mexico
city was earlier called tenochtitlan
and they had their own civilization
their own culture there which was
destroyed by the
spanish conquistadors
hernan cortes and so on brutes
barbarians
and then in north america apparently
there was nothing
so
isn't that extraordinarily strange
that in south america in central america
you had incredibly advanced civilization
civilizations dating back two three four
five thousand years
and in north america you found almost
nothing
you find cahokia you find certain things
uh and yet
nothing much
which is not quite true but the truth is
that
they
do not
encourage
any historical research in north america
into native american history
there are
settlements there also there is
archaeological evidence but it is not
excavated
because if you excavate that then it
becomes very clear
that this this land actually originally
belonged to the natives it was stolen
by the european settlers by european
colonizers who are now in occupation of
the land right
so the native americans are the original
inhabitants of these two continents
and their genetic analysis tells us that
they have a significant amount of
genetic affinity with the people of
eastern asia maybe mongolia maybe
siberia
maybe the ainu people of northern japan
maybe the people of sakhalin and so on
so forth so the native americans have a
significant amount of genetic affinity
with the people of eastern asia all
right
and some people talk about india as well
well thus far there is no evidence of
that there may be but we don't have
evidence because nobody has done any
research and it's also possible that
there could be genetic affinity with
with africa as well but we don't know
for sure now the official story is that
there was no human presence in the
americas until about 13 14 000 years
before today that has been the official
line from the historians well now what's
happened is that they have found human
settlements in southern america in south
america that date back to more than a
hundred thousand years before today so
those
lies are now being debunked right
so it's now becoming more and more
apparent that there has been human
settlement in the americas that dates
back more than a hundred thousand years
before today
and the truth is that the natives are
the true
inhabitants of the land it they should
be the real owner of the owners of the
land
the entire
two continents have been stolen from the
natives by the european colonizers and
settlers and occupiers of these two
continents today native culture has been
destroyed whether it is in mexico
whether it is in brazil whether it is in
argentina where the natives have been
essentially wiped out yeah
or other parts of south america
native culture is almost non-existent
and
in north america it's almost been
stamped out there was a massive
incredibly brutal and cruel genocide
of the native americans in north america
i don't know what the exact number of of
death is maybe a hundred million
possibly who knows
it's never been catalogued
because that would well not look very
good right
because these are the people who now
talk about human rights and all that
so
it's best to keep these things secret
so there was a massive genocide of the
native americans their land was torn
gradually
certain treaties were signed and the
treaties were broken
and now
whatever is left of the native american
people in north america they live on
reservations they are treated like
second class or third class citizens
they are discriminated against there is
a very high incidence of crime against
them
there is a great amount of racism
against them they are marginalized they
are oppressed they have very high rates
of suicide alcoholism depression drug
abuse
crime what not
that is the truth about the native
americans i hope they get some justice i
i hope they get freedom again
that would be good
for humanity
so yeah
that's what it is
rama lakshmi says in the previous video
in the previous video when you showed uh
the forward block of netaji sabashan
rabos it says left wing
which type of ideology do they support
could you brief a little bit about that
okay
the forward block
is
officially classified the all india
forward block is officially classified
as a
left-wing nationalist party
so in india left-wing and nationalist
doesn't quite
make sense right
so it's like this
in 1939
mr bose
was the president of the indian national
congress and then he wa
a political coup was engineered against
him by mr mohandas gandhi
so mr gandhi engineered a political coup
within the congress party against mr
bose who was the president of the
congress party and he was mr bose was
out manoeuvred by mr gandhi
and mr bose had to resign he had to
leave the congress party
or he had to resign from the presidency
of the congress party so what mr bose
did after that is that he established
his own faction
within the congress party his own
political faction which eventually
became a distinct political party he
called it the forward block of the
congress party of the international
indian national congress and this
forward block
uh advocated armed resistance
from british against british occupation
it advocated a violent overthrow of the
british and liberation from india or
liberation for india from british rule
that's what it advocated the overall
congress party advocated ahinsa
non-violence peace love compassion
and that sort of thing right
mr bose said we need to oppose the
british violently and overthrow them by
force so that was a complete break with
the ideology of mr gandhi
so in 1939 this
all india forward block was
created by mr bose mr bose became the
leader of that in 1940 mr bose was
arrested
and
eventually in i think in 41 mr bose
escaped from house arrest he
escaped to northern india to gandhar
afghanistan and through there he went
into russia and eventually ended up in
germany eventually from there he ended
up in japan he started the ina and we
know the story right
so mr bose was associated with the
follower for with the forward block for
a very short amount of time and
in those days
uh
the left ideology was was quite
prevalent and the socialism was
something that mr bose saw
as a means of emancipating the indian
citizens from the poverty that had been
uh
that had been imposed upon them by the
british so socialism was seen as the
vehicle that would take india forward
for a brief period of time and
eventually uh things would change
and
typically outside of india
the left is always nationalistic whether
it is in the ussr
the left which is the
soviet communist party was
greatly nationalistic there were
patriots
even the chinese communist party is
deeply nationalistic anywhere in the
world communist parties
have been nationalists have been
patriots it's only in india that
communists are mercenaries for
anti-india forces
so the forward block was a nationalistic
party yes there were elements of
left-wing ideology of leftist or or
socialistic ideology or communistic or
communist ideology which is okay it was
not marxism it was it was socialism that
they
believed in mr bose most likely believed
in and that's what he wanted to use as a
vehicle for emancipating india and
liberating india and taking india
forward
uh economically
because uh if you look at the way the
ussr developed as a superpower it is
through socialism
uh whether you want to consider it right
or wrong or whatever they did become a
superpower in a very short amount of
time
which is
an incredible achievement
so that was something that could have
been emulated and mr nehru
also espoused socialism but he espoused
the
fabian form of socialism which means no
growth
so that's how it was so that in brief
is the uh all india forward block it
still exists
uh
i'm not sure what role it plays today
it doesn't seem to be a
major
political party today
and i suppose it's not been for a very
long time
so it's associated with association with
mr bose was very short because he
eventually had to go into exile and
after that it was essentially leaderless
so i don't know what the what the
history of this party is who the leaders
have been the only leader of note and
consequence was mr boos so that's what i
can
offer you about this matter in brief
lakshmi sense says in the first world
war when serbia and austria-hungary went
to war
why did countries like germany and
russia come into this war
that's a good question
world war one
which is the beginning of the great
european tribal war
it's extremely complicated it's very
confusing you have to go deep into it to
understand what happened so let's take a
look at the map as always
um
where's the map okay europe we're
talking about europe
so in
1914 the map of europe was different
um
austria and hungary were part of the
same empire the austro-hungarian empire
and you had serbia to the south
so this was the this was the situation
now the austro-hungarian empire also in
in uh
incorporated uh
bosnia and so on
so in 1914 the situation was such that
uh
serbia
had russia
as its ally
serbia had russia has as its ally and
austria-hungary had germany
as its ally
uh
france
was allied
with the with the with the russians
italy was was allied with germany
belgium was neutral
the united kingdom britain was also
neutral in splendid isolation and so
forth okay
so when the archduke franz ferdinand was
assassinated in sarajevo
in
june 1914
by
by a student
what happened is that austro-hungaria
austria-hungary blamed serbia
for the assassination
and it took a month or so but then they
eventually declared war on serbia before
declaring war on serbia they consulted
their german allies
they asked germany is it do you mind if
you go to war with serbia do you mind is
it okay with you and germany said yeah
yeah go ahead go ahead go declare war
so then austria-hungary declared war on
serbia the moment this happened
the russians
declared war on austria-hungary more or
less because they were in alliance with
serbia
the french
were in alliance with russia
the germans took the opportunity of this
war to declare war on france to take
back some territory that had been taken
from them and once
they and the thing is that to declare
they declared war on france but they
could not cross over into france because
the french german border was highly
fortified so to overcome that problem
the germans marched through luxembourg
and belgium the moment they invaded
belgium
the british declared war on germany
because the british were essentially
they were the guarantors of belgium's
autonomy or neutrality so britain got
involved in this and then the germans
invaded belgium there was a lot of
fighting there they eventually came into
france they tried to take paris
eventually the italians got involved
they fought the austrians the
austro-hungarians strangely enough even
though they were part of that uh
triumvirate or whatever
and this was a massively confusing mess
eventually in a few months everybody was
at war so that's the kind of thing that
happened
there were two main alliances and and
once one country declared war everybody
got involved into this
big
conflagration
so that's what happened in world war one
at the end of world war one
the first european tribal war there was
a lot of action in various parts of the
world including in africa including
in in asia
and
even the americans got involved
eventually and the germans were beaten
badly they were humiliated and that
eventually set the tone said set the
stage for the second part of the
european tribal war which was world war
ii
so that is what happened in brief
next the question
man of ashish says what would have
happened if francisco franco francesco
franco spanish dictator would have
joined the axis powers in the second
world war
i mean he could have joined them after
all it was because of hitler and
mussolini's support that he won the
spanish revolution in 1936 1939 the
spanish civil war
so you are right it was because of
hitler mussolini's involvement support
that francisco franco was able to win
was able to prevail in the spanish civil
war which was a nasty brutal civil war
of spaniards fighting spaniards with
outside interference and lots of
atrocities were committed and so on so
forth
so
the spanish civil war was kind of a
proving ground
for the new german technological
advances
in the 1930s the germans started
rearming under adolf hitler the third
reich was formed uh the german military
machine was revived new technologies
that were developed new weaponries new
weapon systems will develop new tanks
new new aircraft new kinds of guns and
all that
and the italians and the germans became
allies mussolini and hitler were allies
and they both aided francisco franco
in the spanish civil war they supplied
him with uh
arms ammunition weapons
logistical tactical support
um advisors and that sort of thing it's
because of that that franco was able to
prevail and he was able to become the
dictator of spain
it was a long protracted campaign
in spain
now when world war ii happened
uh
which essentially bega begins with the
uh invasion
of
poland right it's that's how it begins
so
in world war ii
spain was officially a neutral nation
even though it was inclined to be on the
access side because it had because
franco owed everything he is the rule
his dictatorship his power to hitler and
mausoleum but officially spain remained
neutral they did get involved in certain
ways
in this not
full-fledged fighting but they were
definitely
leaning towards the axis powers but
and yet
spain was not a major military power
spain was not in any way capable of
tilting the balance of the war so even
if they had got involved it would have
essentially harmed spain more
than uh do anything else
uh so i said that spain was neutral but
they tilted towards germany and italy
it it was it became more apparent after
the german occupation of france
so if you look at the map um
what you find is that uh the germans
very rapidly
invaded and occupied france they took
paris they took over the northern and
western part of france and the rest of
france was ruled by the vichy government
i believe yeah
and it is during this time that spain
was
more
outwardly
kind of quasi-allied with with the
germans with the axis powers and so
that's all it was spain was not a major
power in any sense and even if had got
involved officially
and overtly it would not have made any
real difference in the outcome
of the war
all right
next question
let's go
all right apparently it's not coming
all right here we are
this is again by man versus
what was the niedermeyer henthig
expedition
did it prove good for the indians or was
it a failure all right
so this is again something that happened
during world war one world war one is
from 1914 to 19 18 19 20.
look it up listen when i give you dates
you need to double check i don't
memorize dates
i will
sometimes
sometimes make mistakes with dates all
right that is known to happen
i don't memorize dates so in case i i
give you a date you if you are really
serious about understanding this thing
you need to look it up yesterday i spoke
about the interior angles of a triangle
i said that the sum of the interior
angles of a triangle is 360 degrees it's
actually 180 degrees so yeah while
speaking i may make some mistakes
so please double check so the world war
one happened between 1914 and 19
whatever 19 i think yeah
so it was like i said it was a very
complicated affair germany was one of
the major belligerents
and they were fighting the british for
sure yeah
so uh they wanted to
undermine british interests worldwide
let's look at the map once again
so the british
had a massive empire that spanned
significant portions of the world
australia was their colony new zealand
was their colony
india was the jewel in the british crown
they controlled
various parts of the middle east
they controlled the suez canal
the sewers canal was essentially
the uh
the spinal cord the spinal cord of the
british empire
all of their shipping passed through
this all of the logistical supply chains
and supply lines passed through this
waste canal
so if the germans could cut off the
suv's canal it would cut off british
access to their to the to the to india
which would be a disaster for the
british empire which could liberate
india which is why there was a lot of
action in the middle east
turkey
got involved in this turkey allied with
germany yeah
and the germans also wanted to instigate
gandhar or afghanistan
to fight the british so afghanistan at
the time was
kind of an independent nation they had
their own
ruler sultan or whatever amir whatever
you want to call him
i forget the name you can look it up
so they were kind of uh an independent
nation but they were still very much uh
um
in some ways
dependent on the british or kind of
uh
there was a
significant amount of british influence
in afghanistan there were a couple of
wars that the afghans had with the
british and eventually there was a
stalemate and uh
the durand line was drawn between
afghanistan and british india which
still exists as the pakistan afghanistan
border and so on
so afghanistan
was the wild card in this in this region
the germans
sought
to instigate the ruler of one of
afghanistan
to declare war on british india on the
british and to launch an invasion of
india
that was
what the germans sought to do
and that was the objective of the
niedermayer hentaig opera expedition
which i believe uh
took place in 1915-16
two years
so i think it began it it took off from
turkey
and it was a bunch of germans maybe a
couple of indians may have been involved
i'm not sure mostly it was just germans
right
and uh
they were not quite sure where
afghanistan was
so they took off from turkey they went
eastwards and eventually they made their
way into afghanistan they reached kabul
and they
they tried to meet the amir of
afghanistan they were not given a very
warm welcome they were made to wait a
lot for a long time
eventually they met the guy
but the guy had his own his own dealings
with the british in british india the
british were paying him off to to keep
him uh
pliable and all that
so it was all about for the afghan emir
it was about who gave him give them more
money can the germans give more money
can the germans offer him protection
against the british not quite so right
so the mission was not quite successful
they were not able to convince the
afghan
king ruler whatever
to launch an invasion of india even if
he wanted to he was not in the position
of doing that yeah
and
one of the things that contributed to
the failure of the niedermayer hinting
operation expedition
is drunkenness
so afghanistan was an islamic emirate
islamic country
and these germans were found of drinking
and apparently a few of them got drunk
on the streets of kabul
and the people of kabul had never seen
someone drunk so it was a shocking
thing to happen and that is kind of
something that
that contributed to the failure of this
expedition so
that's what it was
so to sum it up it was a failure it did
not succeed
okay a couple of questions about
cheetahs myron says how did india's
cheetahs go extinct did the emperor
akbar kill them all kill all of them
alone
and prasad says what are your thoughts
on india bringing over a dozen cheetahs
from namibia
do they possess any virus that could
potentially harm indigenous wildlife in
india
okay question one is how did india's
cheetahs go extinct
did emperor akbar kill all of them and
no but was not capable of harming
anything but yeah well whatever so uh it
is known that uh during the time of
akbar's son saleem salim his name is
salim right jahangir was his official
title so this individual jahangir who
was a drug addict and a drunkard
he was fond of these cats indian
cheetahs and
i believe he had five thousand pet
cheetahs
i'm not sure if if there are five
thousand cheetahs all over the world
even today you know so that's how many
cheetahs used to be in existence in
india
so what happened to the indian cheetah
about a century or so ago they went
extinct because of the british the
british exterminated the cheetah the
reason for this is that the cheetah was
considered by the british to be a
nuisance a pest that killed via that
killed by a
livestock
and uh
so they decided to exterminate this
animal i like the way you would try to
exterminate mice or rats
so they
put a bounty on the head of the cheetah
they said they would pay whatever price
if you brought back a head of a cheetah
or a tail of a cheetah so suddenly the
indian citizens who were in incredible
poverty
they found a new way of making a little
bit of a little bit of money and you
know
having a better life for some time so
then there was this big hunt for
cheetahs and eventually the cheetah was
wiped out hunted down and destroyed
and it went extinct from india and many
of these indian puppet maharajas also
contributed to that so they would host
british
officers and they would go on these
shikkars
hunts in which they would kill lots
incredible numbers of indian animals
elephants and rhinos and
lions and tigers and cheetahs so that
also contributed to the
eventual extinction of the indian
cheetah so the indian cheetah is
extinct it's gone
the
the population the overall population of
indian chitta some of that still exists
in
to the west of india in persia so a few
cheetahs are still alive they still live
in iran
the indian government has been trying
for for a very long time for several
decades they were they were requesting
the iranians to send a few cheetahs to
india so that we can revive our cheetah
population but it never quite worked out
the iranians never quite agreed
yeah they kept india dangling so now it
looks like indian the indian government
has decided to import i don't know a
dozen or so cheetahs from namibia
so today i think the the nation with the
greatest with the largest cheetah
population is namibia
so we are importing cheetahs from
namibia so in the past i've spoken about
this that the african
wild cats they have certain viruses that
are not present in indian wild cats or
indian cats one of these is the s is the
fiv the feline immunodeficiency virus
fiv
which is similar to the human
immunodeficiency virus hiv right
so uh i believe the indian wild cats
don't have this virus as far as i know i
may be mistaken yeah to the best of my
knowledge the indian cats don't have it
so uh and the
african wildcats as far as i know they
they may have this virus right
so if you import these cats
could it cause trouble
it could possibly i'm not sure it looks
i i hope that the indian government
would have taken this into account and
maybe maybe the
the risk is not that great possibly so i
am sure they must have taken an informed
decision a considered decision
and they must have taken done all the
risk analysis etc so hopefully this
scenario doesn't exist and
there there will be no problem
so
i am hopeful that they would have done
that
so that's what i can say but yeah as
long as there is no risk it's a great
step we will have cheetahs in india
again which is great
because the cheetah was an integral part
of the indian landscape just like they
were just like the deer and various
other animals so it would be great if we
have cheetahs back in the country again
it's it's a it's a landscape that is
tailor-made for the for the
for the survival and the thriving
of these beautiful wildcats so overall
good thing
okay rohit says your thoughts on the
indian navy flag and atharva says i
respect the three indian defense forces
a lot the thing that makes me sad is
that they still
use
the same symbols and flags of the uk
army just replacing the crown with
ashok's thumb
their ceremonial red coat in the
presidential bodyguards uniforms why
can't our government make new ceremonies
uniforms ceremonial uniforms and ditch
the old ones
also changing the logos to something
original and also indian they still have
lots of colonial traditions that could
that could be ditched like the ball
dance etc
okay so what are we talking about let's
take a look at the indian navy flag to
to understand what's being referred to
here
let me
put that up on the screen
indian navy flag
let us see
so what is the the flag or the emblem of
the indian navy look like
this is what the indian navy
flag emblem whatever you want to call it
looks like
it is the so-called saint george's cross
which is the flag of the of england with
the indian tri-color
in the in one corner and the ashok's
thumb in the in the center
my question is why do we need the saint
george
uh cross why do we need the flag of
england
as them as the mainstays the main part
of the of the flag of the indian navy
why do we need that
isn't this a symbol of our continued
colonization and
slavery so this is a very
legitimate question
one has the greatest respect
for the indian armed forces
our our
soldiers our officers
they they
serve the nation they put their lives on
the line every single day one has the
greatest of respect for them
but why do we need to continue the
colonial symbolism
why do we need colonial emblems on
on
the symbols of our military i just don't
understand this
there is indeed a significant need to
decolonize
the armed forces
i am not saying we need to change the
way they operate remove the colonial
symbols it is shameful that we are still
continuing this let me give you a
different example
one second
all right let's take a look at this let
me share this
on the screen
so if you look at the indian aircraft
any of the aircraft in the
in any of the airlines on in india
you have this uh
this
these two letters that are written vt
on all of the aircraft whether it is air
india whether it is uh whatever other
airline it is it's always vt vt
something
right whether it's indigo
or or whatever else
what does vt stand for
it stands for either victorian territory
or viceroy territory
which again is something
left over from the colonial era why
can't we remove this
you know these small things you may say
it's not important it's very important
all of these symbols all of these
symbols are very important they permeate
into the psyche into the consciousness
into the subconscious of the nation it
keeps people
colonized and enslaved
and there are lots of people who will
say what are you talking about why are
you wasting our time on this it's a what
is a big deal if there is some vt
written somewhere what's the big deal if
there's a saint george's cross on on our
naval flag what's the big deal
it's the same people the same people
are going to complain
about lions having their mouth open
on the indian national emblem
they understand the power of symbols
yeah the same people who will complain
that the indian emblem on the new
parliament building is overly aggressive
they are the same people who will say
that we should keep the saint george's
cross
on the indian naval flag and we should
keep vt on the indian aircraft
i am very clear about this we need to
decolonize india
we need to remove all these leftovers
from the colonial age the the great
writer the nobel prize winner vs nepal
who was of indo-caribbean origin he
visited india he was deeply pained by
what he saw in india he when he came to
india he was hoping to reconnect with
the land of his ancestors he was hoping
to see something great and what he saw
was was was pretty able was pts
and he has written this
that uh
when he visited india for the first time
i think it was in the 1950s or 60s most
likely 50s
he went to uh an indian army officers
mess
and even in the 1950s there was a
portrait of the british queen
on the wall
in the indian
army officer
mess or canteen or whatever so they
still regarded
these officers of the indian army from
the of the time they still regarded the
british monarch as their
as their as their monarch apparently
they still kept her her photograph or
portrait on the walls
so that kind of demonstrates the kind of
mental colonization that was there at
that time and one wonders how much of it
is still prevalent today because many of
the traditions
especially at the officer level in the
indian armed forces are continuing just
the same
right
so these things need to be looked into
it's been more than 70 years how long
has it been since 1947
more than 70 years yeah more than seven
decades i think it is time for india to
become properly independent and ditch
all the colonial customs yeah
it is not going to impact the efficiency
or the firepower of the armed forces
it's going to liberate them mentally
so with the greatest of respect with the
greatest of respect and gratitude for
the armed forces i say that we need to
decolonize all aspects of the armed
forces and all aspects of all aspects of
india remove the vt
from the indian aircraft from indian
airplanes and and change it with
something more appropriate
and other things like that why do we
need the saint george's cross
on the indian naval flag it doesn't make
any sense to me or any right singing
person
so yes i agree with
what is being said here and it it should
happen it should it should be taken up
for sure
okay next
swarup says why did the u.s house of
representatives pass a legislative
amendment that approves a waiver to
india against the punitive katsa
sanctions
for its purchase of the s-400 missile
defense
system
from russia do they need india that
badly
so what is the katsa c-a-a-t-s-a
i believe it stands for countering
america's adversaries through sanctions
act
so essentially it means that if you
if if a nation that
if a nation
arms ammunition weapon systems whatever
from one of america's enemies
then the americans can impose sanctions
on that nation
and as we know india has been purchasing
russian weapon systems for a very long
time for decades
and recently
india acquired the s 400
missile defense system which is the most
advanced missile defense system thus far
now the s500 is also there
and the s550 may also be under
development but yeah india purchased the
s400 system
now the turks
turkey
also purchased the s400 and the
americans
uh punished them immediately they cut
off a turkey from the f-35
program the f-35 stealth fighter plane
program the turks are no longer allowed
to acquire this fighter plane even
though they are part of nato even though
they're an official u.s ally
so there was immediate retaliation
against turkey i'm not sure if cats are
the full force of cancer has been thrown
at turkey but there has certainly been
punishment
or that has been imposed upon turkey in
the case of
india the americans were threatening for
quite some time that we are considering
imposing cats are sanctions on india
india certainly is a candidate for qatar
because india has acquired the s400
system we can give you something else
don't acquire don't don't buy russian
weapons buy everything from us from
america and become our you know allies
or whatever that's what they were saying
india did what is best for india because
this is the best missile defense system
that exists currently and it's the right
thing
considering india's national interest
right so then the americans were
were bloviating they were saying we will
impose sanctions but eventually as we
know now
the so-called uh not the so-called the
house of representatives has passed an
amendment a legislative amendment
that uh approves a waiver
for india
from the qatar so why is it so it's
because india is currently indispensable
to the us as a counterweight to china
the americans want to utilize india
on the geopolitical chess board as a
counter balance as a counterweight to
china it is india is the only nation in
asia
that
can
conceivably
challenge china economically militarily
etc it's the one nation that china
actually fears even though they will
never say it and they conceal their fear
of india under
under under this pretense of of uh
contempt
so if you look at the chinese uh
social media accounts if you look at the
global times what they write
they kind of
right in us in a mildly contemptuous
stone about india
um
so they hide their fear in in in that
manner of course they do have a little
bit of contempt for india because india
has not developed the way it should have
yeah
india is still a very much colonized
nation even today so yeah some of that
contempt is justified the chinese don't
quite respect india a lot
but yeah they do respect certain things
that india is able to do now yeah so
it's it's a mixed kind of situation the
point is this the americans if india
is no longer in the american camp
then india
could find ways of going firmly into the
chinese russian camp and and and make
some sort of compromise there it's
certainly possible
it certainly is possible the chinese
cannot cross certain lines when it comes
to india but we could cooperate in
certain manners which would not be good
for the americans so the americans want
india on their side in the uh
in the ongoing geopolitical realignment
of the world
and they want to use india against china
in a variety of ways and india is very
much a part of the quad quad is india
australia japan and the us australia and
japan are u.s vassal states japan is
under u.s occupation australia is a u.s
colony
so it's essentially india and the us
that's what the quad is
so without india
uh the quad doesn't work and the quad is
essential to in to the us
indo-pacific strategy of containing
china so because of these regions
reasons they need india india is
indispensable so india has got its
calculations geopolitical calculations
right
and the americans have been left with no
option
but to
offer a waiver
to cancer to india so
that's what has happened
says if china decides to become india's
ally for the short term should we shake
their hands what are the pros and cons
you said in the joshua versus
video
that china seems to gain some respect
for us is that really a possibility uh
let me once again reiterate there is no
jai shankar against ajit duval scenario
mr doctor jaishankar and mr duval are
working
for india
their objectives are completely aligned
the jaishankar doctrine is essentially
is actually a manifestation of a much
larger modi doctrine and mr duval and mr
joshua and dr jayshankar are both
working to the same
in the same direction in different
spheres so there is no conflict between
the two
any such notion is baseless okay let me
just double reiterate that
now
uh
if china decides to become india's
allies no china will never become
india's ally
but there can be
cooperation
between india and china
uh in in a variety of ways there could
be economic cooperation between india
and china there could be diplomatic
cooperation between india and china the
chinese will cooperate with
nations
whenever there is something to gain
and so will india
there will be issue based cooperation
there will never be a full-scale
alliance india and china are natural
rivals right now as long as there is a
common shared border between india and
chinese occupied territory india and
china are destined to be rivals the same
way that china and russia are natural
rivals currently
there is an understanding between china
and russia because they have a much
bigger opponent to
uh counter which is the us
so currently china and russia are
cooperating
and the chinese know that they cannot
cross certain lines with russia russia
has incredibly overwhelming firepower
they can
they can send china back to the stone
age yeah the russians can do it so the
chinese respect that they respect
the hard edge that the russians have the
the fire power that the russians have
have and that's why they're able to
cooperate
right
similarly
india also has the same sort of
firepower today that the russians have
not
to that extent but india can certainly
also send china back to the stone age if
if need be if the chinese make it
imperative for do for us to do that so
when you have that sort of mutually
assured
destruction mutual respect
mutual fear
then there is a certain basis for
cooperation
so india and china don't have warmth
towards each other the chinese communist
party sees india as a long-term rival as
a wrong long-term enemy as something to
be is a problem to be solved eventually
that's how they see it but for the short
term there could be cooperation
and as india rises economically
um
china would
possibly if the rise happens let's say
in the next 10 15 years india reaches
the 10 trillion dollar economy status
then the chinese would essentially have
no option but to shake hands with india
and to make peace with india
because a rising power
is is a massive threat if you if you try
to antagonize
a power that has so much potential which
is rising which is going to keep rising
it's going to be bad for you
so it is a possibility if india rises
further we need to first reach the 5
trillion mark
then the 10 trillion dollar mark once
india reaches the 10 trillion dollar
mark the relationship will become very
different even at the 5 trillion dollar
mark the relationship will be different
it all depends on the leadership
you may be a small nation
you may be a small economy but if you
have robust leadership
with with a clarity of of vision then
things become easy
then even large powers will respect you
yeah
so right now the situation is that the
chinese don't like india they fear india
but they respect the leadership they
respect the direction that the
leadership is taking the clarity of
thought geopolitically in international
affairs the clarity of thought from the
military perspective and the economic
perspective that is something that
chinese have no option but to respect
so when that sort of situation is there
there is a potential for issue-based
cooperation
so that is what we could see in the
future and of course
there is a bigger threat for china which
also actually
even india could see a threat right the
the empire that controls the world which
actually doesn't doesn't wish india well
or china well
uh so yeah there is
some common ground that india and china
both have and there could be cooperation
and there could be multilateral
electoral cooperation between india
china russia possibly even iran that
could happen
so the west would consider that to be an
the formation of a new access
brics is part of that axis apparently in
their in from their perspective so yeah
that's the kind of geopolitical
situation that is emerging
multi-polarity
the americans want a bipolar world the
chinese eventually want a unipolar world
india france russia iran want a
multipolar world not quite iran but
india fronts russia for sure so there
are three different
competing
world views right now the american
worldview what they want is a bipolar
world they are the good guys and some
bad guy hopefully china the chinese they
have a different worldview the world
they hope for is a unipolar world where
only china rules everybody else bows
down to them
and the world that india and russia and
france are hoping for is a multi-polar
world and many of the smaller nations
are also hoping for that sort of
scenario to happen where everybody
prospers
where no hegemony exists where there is
an actual rules-based world order so
there are three different
envisaged world views that are competing
right now
and uh so yeah that is the game that is
being played as of today
okay zina says can india become the
world's number one military power in the
future i know it needs economic
development what would what should india
focus on as in defense equipments
um
yeah if the indian economy rises if the
indian economy grows india could become
the world's number one military power i
mean if you have a large economy you
have to have a large military what's the
point of having the greatest economy in
the world all these riches all this
wealth all this prosperity if you cannot
defend it
right
so that is the lesson that india has
learned from the past 1000 years of
humiliation
and as india's economy grows india's
military strength will also grow in the
at the same rate
so yes india can become the world's
number one military power in the future
for sure what kind of
focus does should the india indian
military have
it's very simple
the first thing you must focus on
is to make yourself impregnable
you must first focus on defense
when you play cricket
if you're a bad
if you're a batsman batsman better if
you're a batter the first thing you're
taught is how to defend
how to defend right you need to first
focus on the defense once your defense
is imprint is impregnable then you focus
on the attacking shots similarly
in warfare in strategy
in empire building in in nation building
you have to first focus on defense make
sure that your defenses are watertight
that your the nation
is impregnable
you have to develop a defensive
capability fast india for the past 70
years maybe thousand years has only
focused on defense and that too
imperfectly badly so first we need to
make our defenses impregnable what does
that mean lots of missiles you attack me
i'm gonna blow you out of the water
i'm gonna annihilate your forces
first focus on defenses so it doesn't
have to be high tech very high tech we
need lots of planes numbers matter
quantity has a quality of its own we
need lots of aircraft fighter aircraft
interceptors
lots of missiles brahmos missiles
various other missiles artillery pieces
we need lots of
naval assets we don't need very
expensive naval assets we already have i
don't know how many two aircraft
carriers please not not any more than
that
we need lots of submarines we need lots
of missile boats cheap
cheap assets which which can deliver a
big punch
you can build a missile boat for 10
million dollars which is peanuts and you
can put three brahmos missiles on that
imagine if you have a hundred of such
missile boats deployed in the indian
ocean region that is a formidable threat
for for the same price as one aircraft
carrier
so one has to
uh
focus on such things focus on defense
first focus on on
on securing your perimeter
securing your borders and once
you are in a position where it is
insanity
for any
other power to attack you that's where
you can focus on offense
on possibly going beyond your borders
and taking the fight to your enemies
territory because
the number one rule
in warfare is don't ever fight on your
territory
take the fight to the enemies territory
in the entire history of china whenever
they have been forced to fight on their
own territory they have lost
[Music]
the number one rule
in the playbook of the great
emperor sri changes khan
was never fight on your territory always
fight on the enemy's territory so what
india needs to do is first focus on
defense make make india's defenses
impregnable make the military so
powerful that it would be insanity for
anybody to consider attacking india and
then focus
on offensive capabilities so that's what
india can do it should do it can be done
on a budget you don't need to focus on
extremely expensive equipment
focus on quantity
and keep the quality you don't need
extremely high quality
so that's the kind of thing india could
do and yeah obviously one can
one needs to focus on cyber warfare
space warfare on on
hybrid warfare drone warfare and things
like that which is actually quite cheap
you know so yeah these things should be
looked into
okay let's take a few more questions
anurag says
can't dictatorship be positive there
have been a few examples of good
dictators what if india comes under
dictatorship listen
all kings
are dictators aren't they of course no
dictator can rule on his or her own you
need
a group of people who whom you depend on
because you you have to
you need people to carry out your your
orders your policies
uh and so on so forth yeah
so all kings are dictators all emperors
are dictators all queens are dictators
throughout human history we have a
dictatorial system
monarchy aristocracy autocracy whatever
you want to call it and even in the 20th
century and 21st century we've had
dictators who have been good
it's called benevolent dictatorship
uh you can think of a couple of examples
um lee kuan yew of singapore was nothing
but a dictator
he was a dictator but he was a
benevolent dictator right he uplifted
the
the city state of singapore from a third
world country status to a highly
developed country status in just a
generation 20 30 years
his rule was iron fisted it was hard
but he was fair he was just over overall
there could have been a few exceptions
here and there but you can disregard
that yeah
overall
statistically he was a good man a good
good good ruler a hard ruler iron fisted
ruler but overall his rule was good for
the country so that is an example of
benevolent dictatorship joseph keto the
founder of yugoslavia who fought the
nazis in world war ii
he was
he can be considered to have been a
benevolent dictator he was a communist
but
his flavor of communism socialism is
called tito ism i think yeah and it was
a more relaxed form of communism and it
it was good for his nation yugoslavia
developed well and the people were
reasonably well off and so on so that's
another example of a benevolent dictator
a third example could be mustafa kemal
ataturk the dictator of turkey who
brought turkey out of the middle ages
and formerly into the 20th century who
the guy who fought and won the turkish
war of independence from the european
powers who established the the
modern secular nation republic of turkey
yeah
he forced the turks to modernize
and and yeah so that's another example
of a benevolent killer
uh some of his methods may have been
well you could consider them to be
slightly brutal
slightly brutal but yeah overall he was
a benevolent dictator so yeah
that's how it is so dictatorship can be
positive
not all dictators are evil uh
there are certain examples in africa as
well
thomas sankhara i believe was one of
those
he was a good man i believe and so on
yeah so there are some examples of good
dictators
and and see when when when it comes to
india there's no point speculating
so
i will not go into that matter but yes
dictatorship can be good depending on
the person and the system
all right all right let's take a look at
a couple of more questions um
lux says my dad says our ancestors who
lived thousands of years ago lived far
healthier lives and were superior to us
both mentally and physically is he right
in thinking this have modern
conveniences the pollution in the air
the chemicals in our food combined with
a sedentary lifestyle that doesn't
entail much physical work
made us weaker than ever
there is more than a small element of
truth to what your dad says
um
it's true that technologically we are
way more advanced than we have ever been
as far as we know yeah
we have the convenience of modern
technology we are able to communicate in
this manner i'm able to reach out to you
and speak with you all yeah we have
good lives reasonably good lives
we can travel in airplanes
we have all the
conveniences of that modern lives that
modern life offers us because of
technological advances right
so yeah that's great but health wise
people are suffering today
everybody is sedentary everybody sits
all day in offices in cubicles at home
uh there is a great deal of leisure
there is very little physical activity
nobody even sees the sky anymore no one
sees the sun anymore nobody takes in
sunlight
lack of vitamin d a lack of physical
activity
you don't even
commune with nature anymore nobody
plays in rivers anymore no one knows
what wildlife is like because
you don't get to see it
um there are all these lifestyle
diseases lifestyle issues diabetes is a
major major issue worldwide nowadays
obesity is a very big deal in the
developed world increasingly in india
so lots of issues yes there are all
these issues that exist today
the air is increasingly polluted
there is deforestation there are
chemicals and preservatives and food
yeah so
there are problems today that never
existed earlier
so health-wise
whether it is physical health or even
mental health i think our ancestors
maybe a thousand years ago uh
we're better off than us that is quite
possible that there is a significant
amount of truth in that i would say that
you know when it comes to your diet
there should be a very simple rule if
your ancestors did not eat this a
thousand years ago don't eat it so today
you have all the fast food french fries
and pizza and pasta and processed foods
and whatnot
it's best to keep to cut that out you
know
if people did not eat it a thousand
years ago don't eat it today so that is
a very simple rule of thumb that will
essentially prevent lots of health
issues
so
uh
so yes i kind of agree with your dad
there is a significant amount of truth
in what is what he is saying
physically they were much healthier
mentally i think they were much better
off than us
uh so that way yes
they were better off our ancestors than
what we are today
reserved says what
is standard of living exactly is it
related to countries economies
so is it correct to say that with the
decline of the west and the rise of
china the standard of living in china
and india has also increased
um the standard of living is indeed tied
is indeed connected with the country's
economy uh the larger your economy is
the better your standard of living
typically
it depends on your nation's gdp but more
importantly it depends on your nation's
per capita gdp which means your nation's
gdp annual gdp divided by the population
so let's take a look at uh
nations ranked by gdp
let me share my screen just give me a
second please
let's take a look at
the rankings to get an idea of what this
means
okay this is gdp per capita
and it is sorted by
purchasing parity
um
purchasing power parity so qatar is
number one
the gdp per capita in qatar the nation's
gdp divided by the population is 128 000
then you have macau
which is a tiny nation state again
then luxembourg singapore very high very
high brunei ireland uae kuwait
switzerland san marino so if you look at
these countries these are countries that
you would consider to be very affluent
countries right very african nations
hong kong norway the us
iceland the netherlands saudi arabia so
and so on so it is very clear that the
standard of living
is intrinsically related to the per
capita gdp of a nation where does india
figure in this
so india's per capita gdp for china it
is 16 000
and
where is india
india it is 7 000
india is in 122 position number 122 on
the list
where is china
china is number 79
on the list
so what does standards of living mean it
means
how good of a life can you afford to
live
how much money do you have
and what does that money translate into
in terms of the standard of living the
quality of life
can you live a good life do you have
access to clean water good food
luxuries consumer goods and so on
do you have good infrastructure in your
nation good roads good transportation
good schools good governance and so all
of that all of that put together is your
standard of living the level of
prosperity yeah and that obviously is
intrinsically related to your per capita
gdp in your nation so that is in short
what in brief what it is so uh the west
it is declining geopolitically it has
not yet declined economically yeah
uh china's um
gdp is rising india's gdp is rising so
as the gdp rises the standards of living
rise people become
slightly progressively more and more
prosperous
and you can see that in india when i was
a little kid i remember seeing people
walking barefoot on the streets
and the way the main mode of
transportation for people in india was a
bicycle when i was a little kid i still
have those memories
today it's very different right there is
still poverty in india india is still
classified as a third world country low
income country but
from
the time when i was a little kid today
it's been a big change
so the levels of prosperity even though
they are not great they have increased
they've improved and the standard of
living has progressively improved it is
getting better every single year as the
economy grows expands
and so yeah
so that's how it works so india is
getting better china is getting better
china is
significantly ahead of india as of today
and let's see how it goes all right so
that's what it is
saurabh says british historian robert
toombs wrote an article reviewing the
rrr movie and he criticizes this movie
saying that the portrayal of the nasty
british is untrue
he even said that the british raj was
fair with indians and he even claimed
that this movie is made with
for hindu nationalism and it's a bjp
tool
so please tell us how fair was the
british raj with indians
uh correct his history and his knowledge
of history and so on
the british raj was a monstrous barbaric
genocidal killing machine
it was a tool of extraction
it extracted everything of value out of
india it destroyed india
and it
enriched the uk
at india's expense by the time the
british left india india's life
expectancy was 28 32 something like that
horrible
the average person could expect to live
28 or 32 years
can you imagine how bad that is that's
what they did to india
they committed genocide indeed in india
they engineered hundreds of artificial
famines throughout india famine in south
india feminine northern india feminine
east india west india bombay madras
wherever year after year after year
artificial famines
at least a hundred million indians died
in this artificial famines and
when a region was affect afflicted with
the famine there would be epidemics
if you can't eat if you don't have food
to eat your immune system crashes if
your immune system crashes you are more
susceptible to illnesses and incredibly
horrible illnesses happened
plague typhus what not you know
though that death toll is not counted in
the death toll of the famines
that is again something that they
engineered and when there would be a
famine people were starving they would
force the people to work in exchange for
relief
and the relief material they would give
was less
rations than the p than the uh prisoners
of war
in the auschwitz extermination camp run
by the nazis that is how brutal and
barbaric the british were
the amount of money that they stole out
of india is estimated to be at least
worth
45 trillion dollars in today's money
yeah
the death toll is incredibly horrific at
least a hundred million indians
they destroyed indian society look at
the condition of the so-called tribal
people who did that the british did that
and then they tried to re-engineer
indian society they tried to
impose their foreign religion on india
and it's worked
yeah and they are still interfering in
india's internal affairs so who the hell
is this robot tunes to speak about
the indian movie rrr and say that the
british was fair with indians he is
nothing but
a neo colonial colonizer that's what he
is he is trying to
maintain the mental colonization of
indians and he's trying to defend the
british raj for
he's trying to defend the indefensible
so
what is there to say about such people
they're essentially
defending something that is worse than
what the nazis did
that's what it is so there you are such
people still live today shame
shameful
all right all right let's move on from
here
your favor says what are your views on
sylvester stallone and arnold
schwarzenegger why their movies are so
entertaining
and why that type of actors are not seen
in bollywood oh yeah i was a great fan
of sylvester stallone and arnold
schwarzenegger when i was a kid so one
of the um
yeah
what movies rocky rambo
very entertaining movies obviously some
sort of there is an element of american
propaganda again there as a kid you
don't see that you see the great uh hero
doing heroic things very entertaining so
there was a 1980s where which was the
heyday of silver stallone in the 1990s
was the heidi of arnold schwarzenegger
and yeah these two guys were
bodybuilders silva stallone has a very
inspiring story of rags to riches
he became a big star with the movie
rocky
in which i think he wrote this
screenplay screenplay and he insisted
that he should be the main actor the the
hero in the movie and that paid off
and a very hard working person he still
is very fit
so is arnold schwarzenegger arnold
schwarzenegger eventually became the
governor of california
uh had he not been born outside the us
you could have run for president as well
so yeah
um
interesting people very entertaining uh
inspirational stories for sure
yeah so i used to really like those
movies like their movies as a kid i
still enjoy those movies
um
why are such actors not even bollywood
bollywood is all about nepotism there
are a few good actors and actresses but
they are kind of marginalized they don't
get great rules it's the same four or
five people over and over and over again
in bollywood it's nepotism uh so yeah
bollywood it's worthless in my opinion
there are some actors and actresses who
are definitely good some of them whom i
do respect as artists
but most of them are just i don't want
to even see them yeah so yeah that's
what it is
sanathuybe says do you watch the ufc i
do watch the ufc when i find the time to
watch it i
am a fan of martial arts
uh
yeah but i i i can't remember the last
time i saw it live but i try to catch it
catch some highlights on youtube or on
instagram or whatever sometimes
um so yeah i i do
enjoy watching martial arts i
i'm a fan of that so yeah the answer is
uh nomad roni says how to articulate
without getting nervous or fearful how
to become a great storyteller you want
to develop any skill you to practice
you want to
become a public speaker let's say
your practice
start practicing in front of a mirror
pick a topic give yourself a certain
amount of time let's say three minutes
or five minutes or ten minutes and speak
non-stop
speak non-stop don't allow yourself to
stop so speak or maybe you can take a
camera a cell phone and record yourself
and then force yourself to watch
yourself speaking yeah do it over and
over and over again always have an
objective a certain topic and a certain
time period i am gonna speak about this
topic for this many minutes
start with three minutes and break the
topic down into three four different uh
subsections
and keep that in your mind or keep that
in on on a piece of paper in front of
you and practice practice practice
practice every single day for three
months four months five months
once you are fluent in that once you
feel it's natural start
practicing in front of an audience start
with two people start with your brother
and sister start with a couple of
friends once you get comfortable with
that expand the audience and that's how
it goes yeah
practice it's all about practice there
is no substitute for hard work
all the best
okay let me take a couple of questions
from the live chat
yes live chat questions if you have any
let's have it
and if there is anything interesting i
will pick up a couple of questions
um
harsh says can you please shed some
light on the current geopolitical
scenario in antarctica
well um if i were to be funny i would
say that the geopolitics has been played
by penguins and seals but no um
antarctica is currently uh
a place where uh
multiple nations have made claims to
territory but i think there is a
convention that nobody will make will
actually acquire territory there so
right now the the the continent is being
used for scientific research multiple
nations have scientific research
stations there india has at least two
scientific research stations there
dakshin gangotri and something else the
chinese have three four research
stations the americans are there the
argentines argentines are there and so
on
so uh there could be a lot of resources
in antarctica
maybe oil and gas and minerals and all
that so in the future there could be
action there right now
there is a
kind of sense of balance there and no
one is allowed to
exploit
antarctica at all there is zero
commercial exploration as of today maybe
it could change in the future as long as
the u.n exists and all things will stay
this way
but
who knows what's going to be there in
the future so that's what it is
what is zero raise to zero it's indeed
it is undefined
i would like to know your opinion about
communist i think i have made my opinion
clear about communist multiple multiple
multiple times when it comes to other
nations they are patriots when it comes
to india india's communists have always
been internationals for whatever reason
maybe some of them are nationalistic but
overall
the communist party parties whatever
have typically been mercenaries for
foreign powers and the communists have
this stranglehold on the indian
education system on the indian various
institutions etc which is
harmful for the nation the effect has
been overall harmful for india
all right
let's see if i can see some other
interesting questions
ask me something new please
[Applause]
after 50 years can we see indian
military bases all over the world who
knows what's going to happen tomorrow it
may happen who knows who knows maybe
maybe not we don't know
if i were to answer it's just
speculation it's possible
uh
[Laughter]
uh hipp says recently in the farewell
speech of boris johnson
he advised three things to the new pm
who were to be of which the first was
stay close to the americans
this should nail the fact that the uk is
indeed a vasal state of the us indeed
indeed that's what boris johnson said
stay close to the americans or something
to that effect
so the us the uk is nothing but a colony
of assad state of the us and the uk
economy
essentially depends on only on one thing
money laundering that's all it is that's
the only value it provides to the world
money laundering nothing more than that
all right let's see if i can take one
more question
um
okay i think we're done i don't see
anything interesting
lots of comments and so on but yeah
all right my dear friends
done for today
over two hours again so thank you very
much for all the questions great fun as
always talking to you all uh thank you
to all of you who have commented who
have asked questions
uh who have contributed in any way or
the other to the channel thank you very
much i really appreciate it and i will
see you in the next session until that
until then take care thank you
bye